Enchant me. Simplify my life. Make me amazing. They're
incredibly one-sided wedding vows, and the three key principles
underlying the Android team's creative vision for the platform
and the apps that run on it. As engineers,
it can sometimes be difficult to see past our
own delight at harnessing the power of an sdk
to bend a machine to our will, but ultimately,
our goal must be to create that same empowering experience
for our users. And we do that by creating apps
that are as esthetically pleasing as they are functional and
easy to use. Users judge the quality of your app
within the first 30 seconds. It may not be fair,
but a disproportionate amount of that judgement will be based
not on the functionality, but on the visual aesthetics. Does
it look polished? Does it look professional? How easy is
it to use? More than just looking pretty, the entire user
experience is critically important. With 30 seconds to
win users over, it's critical that that onboarding process
the time and effort required to go from downloading
your app to performing it's main function should be
as short and frictionless as possible. Not only
that, but a well designed app should evoke a
visceral reaction that speaks to the subconscious. It should
be fun to use. It should surprise in delightful
ways through subtle animations and smooth transitions that contribute
to a feeling of power and effortlessness. It should
let users touch and interact with objects directly rather
than having to use buttons and menus. And it should
use rich imagery and pictures in place of lots
of words and long sentences. It allows users to
customize your app, to make it theirs while providing
beautiful and sensible defaults. Create something that works like magic,
learning your preference in the context provided by
the device so it never asks users for information
that they've already provided. Provide simple shortcuts to complete
complex tasks, and remember data settings and customizations making
them available across every device. While it's good practice
to create a familiar and welcoming experience by creating
a look and feel that's consistent with the platforms
styles and themes, it's just as important to remember
that this, and all the other principles I've discussed
here, are really just a starting point for your
own creative vision. Deviation from the guidelines is encouraged,
but when you do do so, deviate with purpose.